or maybe he's still trying to get his zoom in order.
- Can you hear me?
- I can hear you.
- Yeah.
- This has been a truly dramatic, like, point of view.
(laughing)
I'm zooming you from my phone
because I could not get my computer to zoom in.
I'm so sorry.
I am one of the recalcitrant nerds who insists
on continuing to use Linux,
even though everyone else has abandoned it.
And I use zoom every day with no trouble,
but I was told by your system
that I needed to upgrade my zoom.
And so I've spent the last 20 minutes
trying to upgrade my zoom.
(laughing)
So hard, so hard.
I know, so now I have zoomed you from my phone,
which is probably what I should have done in the first place.
And so I'm really, really, really, really sorry.
Thank you for your patience.
- Oh, no worries, Ben.
We are so thrilled to have you here.
I just wanted to give you a little bit of a preview
of what's been going on prior to you arriving.
You know, this event started on Wednesday
and it's a humanitarian mapathon event.
And the goal was to digitize 20,000 buildings
using hot OSM and open street maps.
I don't know if you can see from my virtual background,
but between our two campuses, UCLA and USC,
we each digitized collectively 10,000 buildings
at each school.
So we reach our miles to 20,000 buildings,
which were digitized mostly.
We were working in Indonesia and Sudan, South Sudan.
And yesterday we had back to back to back workshops
around topics of humanitarian mapping,
data science, Python, Jupyter Notebooks, Tableau, QGIS,
all these kinds of tools that I know you're familiar with
with the work that you do and the team that you manage.
So we're all very excited to have you here.
I just wanted to quickly kind of introduce you
with the work that I know that you've done.
So let me just quickly,
I'm just very briefly share my screen.
So you look quite different from your picture here.
- Yeah, COVID's been hard on us all.
- Yeah, yeah, you have this kind of rock star
vibe about you today.
COVID has made us all into, you know, punk stars.
But Ben, you know, if you're from Los Angeles
and are familiar with the type of work
that the LA Times has done over the years,
we know Ben has this kind of data journalist
who has put together a lot of the data,
you know, journalistic stories around the LA Times
and our local communities.
I happen to, let me see,
know about Ben's work primarily through the pandemic
because when this came about tracking the coronavirus
in California was a site launched by the LA Times
earlier this year.
And Ben led the effort to work with community organizers,
with hospitals to kind of have a one-stop shop
where all this information about the coronavirus was collected.
It's really an amazing resource if you haven't been there.
It has all the almost real-time data statistics
about coronavirus, kind of more focused locally.
So we know we have data from Johns Hopkins,
that's global and kind of more national,
but where do we find neighborhood level data
about what's going on in Los Angeles?
And this is just an incredible resource.
You know, it's full of real-time data graphics
that's updated hourly.
And, you know, unfortunately, it's still relevant today.
You know, back in March, when I first talked to Ben
about this, I was actually thinking, you know,
maybe the last of the summer.
But that's the reality of the moment.
It's an incredible resource with data charts, maps.
And also, what makes this resource so useful
for us in academia is that, you know, Ben's a huge,
as he said, you know, Linux operating systems
about open data.
So, you know, this week we've been thinking so much
about open data, crowdsourced information,
using open street maps.
And the data desk information provided by the LA Times
allows us to really work with data that's transparent,
that's made publicly available.
And this Coronavirus GitHub page is where I believe
Ben's team is contributing to the community
by providing almost real-time data and statistics
about all the information that they're collecting.
So, I'll leave my talk to that
and let Ben take over now.
And once again, thank you, Ben, for joining us today.
- Yeah, thank you.
I had just emailed you a link to my deck.
So, I'm stuck on my phone.
Would you mind calling that up
and just sharing your screen if it's not too much hassle?
- Oh, no problem.
Hold on one second.
- Sure.
I'll spiel for, I don't know, not too long,
but I was hoping to give everybody here an overview
of our team at the LA Times,
the data and graphics department,
kind of what we do, the types of people who are on the team,
the types of things we make,
so you guys can get a sense of, you know,
how these kind of data skills live
within the journalism world.
And then, you know, we can answer any questions
anybody has that really talk about anything
you guys wanna talk about.
And along the way, if you have anything
you wanna know more about,
or if I'm not explaining something good,
just stop me, just talk.
I'm happy to have a conversation
and glad to be here.
So, I also think it's really cool
you guys are doing open street map stuff,
which I myself have dabbled in a little bit,
trying to do one of my hometowns in Eastern Iowa,
where I grew up.
So, well, where to begin?
So, my name is Ben Welsh.
I'm the editor of the data and graphics department
at the LA Times.
And we're a team of about 20 people
who try to use our computer skills to like,
make stuff happen.
And this presentation will give you kind of an overview
of what that ends up being.
So, go ahead and click on.
So, there's me before COVID.
My wife calls this my Bible salesman photo.
And obviously, next is me after COVID.
We already got to this joke though,
so we don't need to stick with it.
Shout out to all the Twin Peaks fans out there.
We can keep going.
And this deck is one that I have presented internally
at our company,
and it initially included some private business figures,
which I've redacted just to not get in trouble.
But I'll give you the gist of what I was trying to get across
when we get to that point, okay?
Keep clicking.
So, the data and graphics department,
its mission, as best as I can articulate it,
is for us to create digital journalism
that's important to the readers of the LA Times,
both in what they want to read
and what they ought to read, right?
With using data development and design.
And by development,
I mean actual computer code development, right?
So the people that are on this team, if you hit the next slide,
are not just reporters and editors and journalists
and people like me who went to journalism school.
They're also at the same time,
computer programmers, data analysts,
information designers, data scientists,
whatever you want to call it, they're nerds, right?
And so, we're kind of one of the more multi-hyphened teams
at the LA Times and that people are called upon
to not just do the traditional skills of journalism,
but also to have these technical skills
that let them find and tell stories in other ways.
And this is something that's increasingly common
across the journalism industry.
Our team is not unique.
There's kind of an evolution happening
in graphics and data departments across the country
where graphics is becoming kind of a higher-skill
data and programming profession.
And our team is caught in the same currents
that are driving that, right?
And so, the people on our team have to be pretty darn flexible.
And so, if you hit the next slide, you can get a look at them.
Like I said, it's about 20 different people.
They come from many of them from Southern California,
many of them from UCLA and USC, or at least a couple,
but also from all across America.
And they're people with a lot of different backgrounds
and skills.
We try to have everybody learn as many
of the different types of things we do as possible,
but the way it works out is some people tend to be
a little better at analysis or maybe a little better
at visualization, but we don't specialize.
We really do kind of try to treat everybody
as being able to take on all of the challenges.
And so, we're always learning and we're always experimenting
and trying to take on new skills.
Just this morning, I was helping someone learn
how to write some spelt, if anybody here is a spelt fan,
to make some of our election graphics for next week.
So, if you hit the next slide, we're gonna get into
what are these things we actually make?
In a lot of ways, to me, a newspaper where I've worked
at the LA Times for 13 years now and seen a lot of change,
but even though we're making different things
and different products, it is kind of an information factory.
So, in a certain sense, a news organization
takes the raw materials of life, of things
that are happening in the world,
and it refines those raw materials into products,
news products that you can sell,
and the people want that help them make sense of the world.
And traditionally, in my painful metaphor,
the assembly lines at this factory were really focused
on making a print newspaper that had blocks of text, right?
With headlines and photos, and that was like,
what the majority of the assembly lines were set up to do.
There were other ones to have sports scores and boxes
and to give you the movie listings
and all these other things.
But in the rewiring of our economy,
that's brought on by the internet and all that,
the factory of the LA Times has to be refitted
with new assembly lines to make different products, right?
That are more in line with what people want
that can compete with other factories out there
in the marketplace, and that can help us shift
to a different type of business,
which is more focused on getting money from subscriptions
and readers who like us enough to pay us
and less so on advertising,
which if you guys are interested in all that business stuff,
we can talk about it later, but I won't be too boring.
And in our little department, it's my view that our assembly,
we basically have three assembly lines
that the people you saw before kind of interchangeably work
on.
The first one makes applications, software websites, right?
The second makes visual stories.
These are stand up, we'll get to those.
And then the third is making digital designs.
And so let's go through those one, two, three,
and I'll show you a bunch of examples of each.
So first up is applications.
This is where we use our software skills
to gather and refine data to serve our digital audience,
writing computer code to go get data,
filing public records requests to get it,
otherwise building databases ourselves from the ground up
that we can then turn into a web application
that is not a traditional story
that people will wanna read and maybe even pay for, right?
And so if you hit the next slide, the first example,
I guess would be the coronavirus tracker.
This is a recent one.
This is where we're gathering data
from a ton of different sources
and turning it into all these pages
that update as frequently as we can get them to,
and let people slice and dice and tailor them.
There's also 58 pages, one for each local county, right?
And we're always working to look and expand on this.
There's a few things I'm hoping we can get out soon.
Yes, that is Netscape.
This is my visual pun for this presentation.
If you'll bear with me, I'm showing my age.
Okay, so then like another example,
if we keep going would be our live wildfires map.
So this is where we're pulling in data
from a lot of public sources and one private one
to try to give people the most comprehensive,
kind of composite view of what's happening
with wildfires this minute in California
or the most recent one possible.
And it's in no way a traditional story, right?
It's a single webpage that updates and stands along.
If you hit the next one,
another example would be our quake bot.
So this is something that isn't like a standalone webpage.
It's something else.
It's a piece of automation.
And so every time there's an earthquake detected
by the USGS, it sends out like a data feed
to the whole world, like kind of little pulses
that say here's the latest earthquake
and how big it was and where it was.
And we have an algorithm that reads every one of those
based on how close they are to Los Angeles
and how high the magnitude is.
We have some sort of editorial barriers.
And then if the data surpasses those barriers,
this blog post is automatically written
and this map is automatically made
and prepared for publication.
And so within a minute of an earthquake happening,
we can have the complete post,
including the map ready to roll.
We still have a human look at it, of course,
before it goes live,
but this is where automation gives us
kind of a quick step out the door immediately.
And then the next one would be, I think,
our most recent police shootings database,
we have a long running project called the homicide report
where we have built from the ground up
our own independent database of every person
killed by another in LA County since the year 2000.
And this year we decided to repurpose a slice of that data
to be a standalone database that just tracks police shootings
and gives people a sense of the latest trends
and that now, like the homicide report,
live updates every time we get new records in.
These databases, they power these standalone applications
and they would probably worth doing just for that reason,
but they also have the side benefit
of allowing us to do enterprise analysis
into these issues that we otherwise couldn't do
if we didn't have the data, right?
So on the next slide, you can see,
since we've been gathering all this COVID data
for months and months,
we've been able to do tons of stories about COVID
that are a little more traditional,
but that have stronger claims and more insightful analysis
because we have this data to draw from.
So one example would be this kind of step back piece
that we did after LA County's sort of botched reopening,
where we were able to use all the data we gathered
and other things we pulled in to kind of tell that story
of what happened here in LA
in a way that wasn't just a data application, right?
And then the next one would come from our homicide report
database.
If you guys follow the news,
you may have heard about the case of Deshawn Kizzie,
who was a young man,
killed following a bicycle stop in South LA
by sheriff's deputies.
And when that happened,
it sort of raised a question of,
well, how common are these bicycle stops
that lead to fatal encounters?
And because we had gathered this database
and had all this information,
we were the only media outlet that was able to give
the public the news that, hey, this isn't a loan incident.
This is something that's happened 15 times
in the last 15 years.
And so it's not especially common,
but it's more common than this being the first time.
And you're able to bring context and insight to it.
You can see if you see that map fly by really quick
that these incidents have been concentrated
in certain areas too.
We have some public records requests out
that I believe will allow us to look into that further
in the future.
So that's thing one,
that's the kind of the applications and the analysis.
We have live election results coming on Tuesday.
So this is all the flowing data feeds
of votes coming in from across America.
We'll go into maps and tables and charts
to help you kind of make sense of what's going on, right?
And so all right, so now we can do thing two.
So assembly line number two is visual stories
is what I call them.
This is kind of an emerging story type
in the world of data and graphics online
that nobody really has a good name for.
So if anybody here has a better name for it,
I'd love to hear it.
You can hit the next slide.
And so visual stories are when graphics reporter reports
and designs visual coverage that is substantial enough
to stand on its own.
Traditionally graphics departments
had sort of made accompanying graphics.
So on the old assembly line,
you might be making a front page story
and you got to have 1600 words of text
and you got to have a headline
and you got to have maybe a couple photos.
And hey, if you're really going to dress up
that front page story, you might get a bar chart
and go with it, right?
And so a lot of graphics departments
had been oriented around being a support desk
that was producing these sort of supplementary graphics
for traditional stories.
And we love those graphics.
They're a good thing, I like them.
But I think we have the potential to do quite a bit more
and I think our audience wants something a little more.
And so one thing I bet everybody here has noticed
reading some of the leading news outlets in America
is that they now produce these visual stories
that are primarily just a combination of graphics
that are big enough that they can just stand on their own, right?
And that's what I call a visual story.
And these are pieces that at most places
are reported, pitched and executed primarily
by the graphics reporter.
It's not a case where a writer of a traditional story
comes to the graphics department and asks for a graphic, right?
So the entire process of how things kind of come together
has changed and the graphics reporter
is more in the driver's seat, okay?
And so go ahead and hit the next slide
and we'll look at some examples.
So early this year, as I'm sure everyone here knows,
Kobe Bryant died in a tragic helicopter accident
near Calabasas and immediately we thought
there's a visual component to the story.
For people to understand what happened,
you need to know the path of his helicopter, right?
And so on day one, it was like a map of where did he crash
and it's just like an X.
And then between day one and day two,
it's like, well, what was the path of the helicopter
and what was really going on and what's the play-by-play, right?
And then what we kind of learned on,
it happened on a Sunday, what we kind of learned on Monday
is like, oh, well, it seems like the final like part
of this helicopter flight is where things really went wrong.
And this was kind of the crucial moment.
And so we decide, well, let's try to do a story
that helps people see or understand as best as we can
what happened.
And so we took the publicly available data about the helicopter
and we turned it into like a three or four step
little graphic here that has, for each chapter in the story,
has like a 3D map that helps you see what's going on.
And by the end, you sort of are able to see
this sort of important thing where the helicopter
began climbing very rapidly in the last few seconds
before a quick turn and then a crash.
And that's the sort of thing that you can describe in words
but is maybe better understood by seeing a 3D model, right?
So the next example on the next slide
would be something from politics.
So we have this very tight DA race, we think.
And after the primary, when we knew we were going
to run off, we get the precinct level results
that show you where people voted in every neighborhood.
And we kind of did an analysis that looked at,
well, where is the incumbent strong?
Where is the challenger strong?
And what would an upset coalition have to look like
based on past election results
and what we kind of know about this election?
So this piece is really about helping people understand
the political calculus of this local race through maps, right?
And then the next one is we did a local mask survey.
So there was this thing over the summer,
the question of how many people are actually really wearing masks
and rather than just quote public opinion polls
or take data from other places,
we decided to conduct our own survey.
So a dozen of our reporters went to three different locations
of multiple times over a few weeks.
We followed a method that Jill Darling at USC
helped us like figure out.
And then we were able to kind of come back
with our own provisional conclusions
about how many people are wearing masks roughly
and the variations between the different locations we looked at.
And then that's presented here
as sort of a designee standalone thing
that's really more about charts and maps
than it is about text, right?
Next slide would be something that's not really data at all.
It's more visual.
And so in the George Floyd protests,
I'm sure everyone saw on social media,
there was a lot of footage of the police here in LA
being pretty violent.
And so we did a piece where we tried to aggregate
as much as that as possible
and then help compare it to the actual standards
for use of force the police are supposed to follow
to show the contrast.
And so this is a case where we're using the design
and the visual graph and the videos to tell the story
and it's not really like charts and maps, you know what I mean?
But it still falls within kind of this
under this visual umbrella that I think is part of what we do
and it's why I call it a visual story
and not a graphic story or something, right?
And we have another example I'm trying to remember.
Oh, and then here's one we did on homeless housing.
This is a type of visual story I bet you've all seen too
that we call scrolly telling, which is a terrible term,
which is where as you scroll things sort of move and happen
and this is another type of visual technique
that we use from time to time, depending on whether it fits
the story we're trying to tell, okay?
I think that's it for those examples.
And then I think we get to things three,
if I remember my deck right, which is digital designs.
Oh, no, it doesn't fit the screen size.
My gosh, you found a bug in my deck,
but this is a case where we're using our digital design skills
to elevate the newsroom's most ambitious journalism
through like what we think
are cool digital custom presentations.
And in this case, we're usually helping to elevate stories
developed by other departments rather than our own work.
And a lot of it has some, you know,
nothing to do with data or graphics.
We're kind of the boutique web designers
for these like flagship projects of the newsroom, okay?
So examples of that wouldn't be on the following slide.
So the first one would be we did an obituaries package
of all the people who died from COVID.
Not all of them of many people who died in COVID,
of COVID here locally.
And then that package has sort of a custom design
to try to make it more dramatic and interesting
and engaging for the reader.
The next example is one from Sunday.
I wonder if anybody here saw it.
We had a piece by Rosanna Shee about DDT
being dumped off the coast back in the day here in LA.
And to try to make that story more impactful and grabby
and to get people we did custom design for it,
which included like a video topper,
which you see here, a little scrolly telling in the middle.
And then the sort of overall design and theme of the page
is customized to fit the story.
It isn't just the generic LA times kind of look, right?
Now the next one is the Chicano moratorium package
over the summer, we had an anniversary
of a famous protest in East LA against the Vietnam War,
which ended up being a series of stories.
And in the past, this might have just been
like a newspaper special suction,
and then a bunch of pages on our website
that aren't really connected.
But what we try to do is to bring a style and theme
to the whole package.
This is kind of the cover page where all the stories
were collected, and then each of the individual stories
was given sort of a variation on the theme
that you see here is the idea.
And I think next up is the one I'm gonna,
oh, then sometimes we do these for other platforms,
not just for the open web.
The Linux nerd in me would love it all just to be
on RWW, but as far as our business goes,
we do need to cross publish these things
on monopolistic corporate platforms, guys, like Apple News.
And so sometimes we will customize stuff
to work on those other places as well,
as you see here with our voter guide,
which ran inside of Apple News.
And then we have, I think the next slide
will just tease one we have coming,
we're gonna try to do a crazier year in review package
that will be more visual and fun
than what we typically done in the past.
So those are the three types of things we do.
The next section kind of gets into what that requires
for a change, and some of this is a little more
in my message for people eternally at the LA Times,
but I think it'll work for you guys too,
which is for this, for our data and graphics department
to make these things and to achieve this mission,
they have to be more independent and ambitious
than maybe a traditional graphics department has been,
and they need to have a higher skill level.
So that requires us to seek out
and develop our own ideas,
to look at the major storylines of the day,
be it COVID or COB or the Dodgers winning
or the election or the George Floyd protests
or homelessness here locally
or whatever those major topics are
that we know both matter to our democracy,
but also to our audience in terms of what they want to pay for.
We need to look at those topics and say,
our job is to develop striking visual and data coverage
that people are going to want,
and that means we have to be more ambitious
than some departments have been in the past.
We need to take more initiative,
and we need to operate more like a traditional news department
in having our own sort of editing system and people in place.
So that's kind of this section.
And you can just jump through the next few slides
and we'll get to where the next section,
I just talk about the results.
So just, you can jump ahead here a couple.
There's Alex Tatuzzi and my deputy editor, my hero.
And then the next slide is our listing.
We have a job listing for a second deputy editor
as we try to increase our editing muscle on our team,
which is one of my major strategic goals
for the current moment.
And the reason we pursue all these goals
is not just 'cause we're nerds and we like to do it,
which is maybe a good enough reason
if you're not expecting to get paid.
But we also are pursuing this different type of journalism.
One, because we like doing it.
Two, because it's better journalism.
The three, because it pays and it's better for our business.
And so the next section is really kind of covers
that these types of things I've been showing you,
they're more popular with audiences.
They're more valuable in that they are seen
to convert more new subscribers to the digital product,
which is our number one business goal than a typical story.
And they're more durable in that they continue
to draw an audience long after they're initially published,
where most new stories kind of peter out within a day or two.
So this next section is all redacted,
so we don't need to look at it, but I can give you the gist.
I mean, you probably aren't gonna be surprised
to hear this if you think about it,
but our coronavirus tracker,
as humble as it may appear to you,
is the most popular page in the history
of the Los Angeles Times website.
No page has ever been visited by more people.
And if you compare it to our top traditional stories,
it is multiple times more popular
than the most popular stories of the year.
And then when you look at conversions
in terms of what's valuable in attracting new paying subscribers,
it is an order of magnitude higher
than the number two story of the entire year.
And so you see that when things like this connect,
they have a sort of home run possibility for the business
that a traditional story very rarely can have.
And then if you look at that over time,
you'll see that it didn't become the top converting story
until three or four months after it had initially launched,
which just shows that it's continuing to draw audience
and new paying customers over time
and that sort of durability I was talking about.
And so for those reasons,
we think that there's a strong business logic
behind investing in what we do.
And I'll kind of close with this, I guess maybe,
but having been a news nerd, as people say,
and having done this kind of thing for nearly 20 years now,
that has been the biggest change
that I have seen in the last five or 10 years.
When I began this as like a computer programmer journalist
in 2000, we were curiosities.
We were either the one person on the investigative team
who had learned to code to try to do a cool data analysis
for a traditional print investigative piece,
or you were some weird person in the corner
who said the internet's gonna be big one day,
and we need to learn how to make new weird things.
And so the justifications for most of the teams
that I've been on in my entire career
were either this is data analysis
to do more impactful and important investigative reporting.
That's actually what got me into it initially
and is still my passion, right?
Or it was this is sort of boutique internet experimentation
to kind of see what comes of it, right?
And we're now far enough into the digital transition
to the information economy
that that's just fundamentally changed.
And what we've seen is that there are certain types
of these products, these data and graphics products
that are so successful
that there's now like a capitalistic economic logic
for producing them.
And there's less and less of a logic
for producing what these departments produced before.
And so that's why I think not to get,
I guess I am at the university
so I can get all Marxist on you guys, you know,
like I think that that is this economic logic
that is driving kind of the evolution of our team
and the justification for growing it,
as well as similar changes you see in other departments
like ours at other news organizations,
some of which are like us in the middle of the transition
and some others are further along down the road.
Like for instance, the New York Times graphics desk
which is already fully converted into this type of thing
that I've been talking about here today.
And I don't work there so I don't know the numbers
but I would estimate based on what we see
and based upon how the number of things they put out
and the quality of what they put out
that like the New York Times graphics department
may be the most read and most profitable department
in the whole newsroom, like that wouldn't surprise me
with maybe the exception of one or two people
who write about Trump, you know.
And that is something that just was not true in the past
when these departments were seen as supplementary, right?
So that's my spiel.
I'm happy to talk about really any of these issues
that were raised, any of the stories in particular,
any, you guys want to talk about Python?
I'll talk D3, I'll talk about that.
Whatever you guys want to talk about,
I'm happy to just jam and hang out.
- All right, well, that was fascinating.
I do certainly want to open it up to the audience
because this is about the students who are here
participating this week.
Maybe I'll have Andy kind of summarize the questions
in the chat room, but in the meantime,
well, you know, go ahead and post questions
that you have for Ben in the chat room,
but maybe I'll kick it off a little bit here, Ben.
You really talk about this kind of transformative age
of data journalism through this kind of visual evolution.
What's just kind of like mind boggling to me
is the fluidity by which you guys go about your business.
Thinking like any one of the products
that you have showcased in your presentation,
if we were to do any one of those in academic institution,
it'll probably take six months to create.
And just kind of, you know, be followed by this,
your ability to, you know, pivot so quickly
with a new story.
And then the next day you have like something
that looks like it took six months to create.
Can you talk a little bit about this kind of this environment
that you work in, the speed that you have to work in?
And you ever sleep?
- Well, I'm glad you think that during COVID, very rarely,
as you can tell by looking at me,
but like after the selection,
the dream is like December, like maybe a day off,
but like,
but more seriously, it's really like any,
like, you know, I like the factory metaphor,
but I'm sure there's other ways to talk about it,
but it's like any process, any like manufacturing process,
you break it down into pieces
and then you like get really good at like, you know,
getting each of those pieces of things
that need to get done kind of like handled, you know,
and you then try to speed up the process as much as you can.
And so like in the case of like a visual story, for instance,
you can think about it in that abstract manufacturing way
in the sense that you need a toolkit
that lets you stand up a single static page
that's outside of like a traditional
rigid content management system, right?
That can be custom coded and designed.
And so what you'll find is that at our department
and every other one like it,
that people have their little quote framework
or their little, you know, publishing rig
that lets them spin up a standalone web page.
And then within that, there's like components
of web development that make it easier for you
to move quickly like a template inheritance.
Well, within that system,
we have a base template that has all the LA time styles
and fonts and the header and footer
and like all the basic pieces.
And so then those are just like there for you
when you like get the page like rolling, you know what I mean?
And you're within that already.
And then by the push of a button,
you can trigger a little deploy
that will send that like blank page live.
And then within the framework, you, you know,
depending on how you set it up,
you have ways to import data files
and then to quickly get them into JavaScript
and other tools so that you can lay out the page
kind of as quickly as possible.
And our system isn't as streamlined as it could be
or as it should be, you know,
but like every, we've developed it ourselves internally
and we're trying to make it better like all the time.
Like this week we were talking about,
well, how could we get it better at producing a headless page
that's for iframing in other places?
You know, how could we make a template
that's just like ready to make an iframe page
that could go on the homepage in 10 minutes, right?
And so you have to have like that toolkit that's there.
You have to have someone on staff
who can like build and maintain such a toolkit
because they don't really exist.
One of my goals is for there to be
a more standard open source sort of like thing for that.
You know what I mean?
You look at tool like when we make an application
like the live election results or the tracker,
we might use Django or some of these
pretty highly developed web frameworks for databases.
But when it comes to static pages,
you really just have kind of like a hodgepodge
of like node framework thingies
that like can kind of halfway make a page
but they don't have the 30 different things
you actually need to make a real page
that you want to publish, right?
And like kind of, I think that there's the possibility
for a stronger open source framework
that goes beyond just the basic tools
and gets into a little more of the opinionated decisions
about how to manage deployment
and static assets and data files and stuff.
Wow, that was way too nerdy.
But like that's part of it.
That's like the technology part.
And then there's the kind of editing and journalism part
which is identifying either planned events
that are ahead on the calendar
that you know are coming like the election
or pivoting when a major storyline emerges
and then focusing your assignment on it.
And so like in the case of like the Kobe thing,
it's like Kobe's helicopter crashes on Sunday.
In a breaking news situation like that,
we tend to think in terms of like rounds of coverage
or stages.
So on day one, we're going to do this.
On day two, we're going to do this.
And then we're going to aim for something
that's like a little more, you know what I mean?
And so like in the case of Kobe,
day one was just like, where is the crash?
What kind of helicopter was it?
You know what I mean?
The basic facts and can you visually do that?
Day two was, well let's get the play-by-play.
What was the like?
When did they take off?
Where did they go?
But you know, so we had a graphic
with the day two story that had that stuff.
Was there a route, a typical route?
Was it an unusual route, you know?
And then what happens typically in that is
after you learn the basic facts,
you kind of get to a point where you're like,
okay, here's what we think the story is.
You know what I mean?
So like within these facts,
here's what we think is worth sort of teasing out
visually for people.
So both has to be something insightful
that goes beyond the basic facts for people,
but it also has to have like a visual component to it, right?
And so in the case of Kobe,
our decision was to focus on the final turns of the helicopter.
All this is of course debatable,
but those were sort of our judgments we made
like in those moments.
Like the conception boat crash,
the fire off Santa Barbara coast,
I guess a year ago now,
was another example of that where day one,
it's just, well, where was the boat? What was the boats route?
Day two, or there are like advanced,
our piece for the weekend then was like,
well, what were the escape routes on this boat?
Where that was what seemed to us to be like the story.
You're kind of betting that that's how it's gonna shake out.
You know what I mean?
As the facts come in.
And then let's make a 3D model of the boats
so we can show people what these escape routes were like
and emphasize that they weren't very good.
You know, it's what it ended up being.
So that's like a breaking new situation.
And then there's kind of in between ones
where it's like there's gonna be this long storyline.
And this is something that we're just trying to really
get better at in our department this year.
And is what I really admire about the New York Times
and some of the more mature departments,
is it seems to me that they have kind of decided on
for the year, here's what their major storylines are gonna be.
And then they come up with a string of visual coverage
to try to attack those major storylines.
And sometimes those can be planned like the election.
And other times like COVID, they just occur
and then you have to be smart pivot, right?
And so for us, we've done that this year
for the Floyd protests and for the COVID coverage
where we put together our own independent visual coverage plan
of like here's ideas.
Everybody in the team pitches things in.
We think about are there applications we could do?
We think about are there visual stories we could do?
And then we try to make them happen.
- Yeah, that's wonderful.
I just wanna jump in.
There's a really, really great question.
I think it can kind of build on what you were,
I mean, what you just talked about.
But the question is about just sort of thought process
and developing stories and data,
but specifically about dealing with biases and storytelling.
And then the follow up to it is,
are there any specific examples that you could share
where you did face pushback on a story
that is sort of data driven,
but maybe there's some sort of part of it
that kind of, you know, there was a stop to it.
- Like internally at the LA Times, that's-
- Yeah.
- Well, you know, or maybe just from you.
Maybe you kind of, yeah.
- I think I have an example, it might not be exactly that.
I will just say I've been here 13 years
and you know, like any institution,
people have disagreements and conflicts and struggles,
you know what I mean?
And I've had my own.
But I will say that in that time,
I have never once felt that if I had a good story
that I knew was true, we couldn't get it published.
That's never happened.
There are people I really disagree with
and to be honest with you, I don't like
and they might not like me,
but I have at different times been able to come to them
with we have the story, check this out, let's do it.
And those people, they rise above all the personal stuff
and they're like, yeah, let's do it.
You know what I mean?
And to me, that's one of the great things about a newsroom
is that people who disagree or who are different
can unite around like a good story.
And like I have nothing but good things to say
about that personally, but like this is an example though
and of something slightly different but related,
which is how and one thing I really love about statistics
is how it can sometimes they can sometimes lead you
to conclusions that you do you would never imagine,
you know what I mean?
Or maybe we're counter to your initial bias
and then you end up telling a different story
than the one you thought you were gonna tell
when it started out, right?
And so you guys remember Hurricane Harvey in Houston.
Oh, I have to send a Slack message really quick.
I have to,
this will just take a second.
I have bought a mechanical keyboard
during this like period at home guys
and it is so loud when I type that this might be deafening
but you guys remember Hurricane Harvey.
This was in Houston a couple years ago.
They had kind of like a big storm come through
and kind of flood the whole place
and it led to these sort of crazy images on television
of people trying to cross the city
in this sort of biblical flood kind of situation.
And it was a Friday night and we were sitting
in the newsroom at the LA Times
and an editor said to me, well, we gotta do something.
Let's come up with something.
It was one of these moments, right?
Like what are we gonna do?
This nuts thing is happening.
We have to come up with a way to cover it.
And like a lot of those situations,
you kind of start with what you're seeing in the news,
what you hear from other people and your own biases.
You know what I mean?
Like what you kind of think about the world.
And like, and then we're trying to come up
with a data story.
And so our initial thought was, hey,
if we get the data about where the FEMA flood zones are,
these officially defined flood zones from the government,
right?
And we compare it to the early damage data
that we see coming in from the government
about where buildings are damaged.
We're gonna find that all the people in these zones
got wiped out and we're gonna be able to add them up
into some big number and try to do a story
about the like extent of the damage, right?
And like, we didn't know exactly what it was gonna be,
but that was kind of our methodological bias
or frame that we like came to it with, right?
Let me just send this message, sorry.
And we're all fired up to do that.
I stayed up to like one in the morning, like it's like,
oh my gosh, the Harris County Property Assessors Office
has all the data online.
Yeah, grab it.
And the FEMA is having a conference call
and they're gonna give out the damage data.
Wow, there's property values.
Here's the flood zones.
I'm gonna put them all together and like find it out.
And like, and then we pitched that story to an editor
and we say, this is what story is gonna be.
It's gonna be about how screwed up Houston got
'cause all this.
And then I did the analysis
and what I quickly found, or not quickly, not so quickly,
what I soon found was that most of the damage
was actually outside of the official FEMA flood zones, right?
So that was an interesting thing.
And then we're like, okay, so let's start calling people
and let's figure out what's going on.
So we're just getting on the phone calling, texting
'cause we have all these addresses
from the property assessors.
Just call every person and just see what's going on.
And we did dozens and dozens of phone calls.
And what we found is that people inside
the official FEMA risk zones were actually like fine.
Like every one of them we could try to was like,
no, I'm good.
We were high.
We had put up like, we had elevated our house
or we had put in a retaining pond
and that caught all the water or our roads got redone.
And it was the people outside who had the problems.
And what we kind of pieced together then
from talking to experts and more and more people
was that our initial assumption was actually reverse.
And that's because believe it or not,
public policy works guys or it can.
It's that if you're inside an official FEMA flood zone,
there were all these additional building requirements
and retrofitting requirements for like taking care
and getting ready.
And so the people who lived in the quote unquote
riskiest areas actually ended up having the best outcomes
because they had to take all these preventive measures.
And so we ended up writing a story about that,
about how, hey, these regulations actually work,
but they're not nearly widespread enough
to save all these other people, you know what I mean?
It's kind of what the story ended up being.
And we had to kind of go back to the editor
and be like, oh, our initial pitch, it's like not that at all.
And that was this, it's a little hard to summarize,
but that was this sort of like weird process
of gathering numbers, listening to them,
talking to people on the other end of the data
and gradually having like a light bulb go on like,
oh, what everything I think is wrong.
And then you have, there's, whenever that happens,
there's always this like fun meeting
like in the middle of it where like you get together
and you're like, hey, we're totally wrong, right?
(laughing)
And you have to, okay, well, we can't just give up.
We gotta come up with like some story.
And so then oftentimes it's a more interesting story,
you know what I mean?
Because it's something you didn't expect, you know?
- Yeah, that's, yeah, that is actually amazing.
And it's really, I think it's just sort of really helpful
to kind of get that perspective on how you develop
and really work through these stories.
Another question, and I know we wanna be really sensitive
of having you here for too, too long,
but we have a couple of really good questions.
One, I think that would maybe really also be helpful
for students is just sort of thinking about
that tipping point between when you're creating a story,
when is it interactive and when is it static
and kind of like, how does that decision process get made
and how does that sort of, how does that happen?
- That's a tough one, and there's not one answer,
but I mean, if the question is when is something interactive?
Look, if you ask it that way,
the answer is less and less so every month and year.
And that has a lot to do with the changes we've seen
in consumer technology over the last five or 10 years.
As more and more people have moved to mobile phones.
Believe it or not, you probably will believe it.
You guys are into tech.
The majority of people who read the LA Times online
read it on a phone, like well more than 50%.
And so in a circumstance where the majority
of your audience is visiting you on a very small screen,
which they mostly just like thumb up and down on, right?
A lot of the interactive graphics that were very intricate
and made in Adobe Flash or whatever, 10 years ago,
really no longer makes sense because most people
aren't gonna interact with them and use them.
And the reality is, is what we learned from web analytics,
even before the mobile changes,
that most people never interacted with them anyway.
And so that's why you've seen a shift in,
if you follow kind of our little niche,
you've seen a shift away from most interactive graphics.
And so for the most part, we're looking for graphics
that can work static and small on mobile
and the way to make them more insightful
is usually through adding an annotation layer,
so like a little swoopy arrow or something.
Or a scrolling change, like you see
in that scrolling technique or the chart sort of changes
as the user continues to read the page.
Where interactivity still makes a lot of sense,
I think is in cases of personalization or of discovery.
So we're gonna have a chart that shows you
the total number of deaths at nursing homes from COVID.
But then when we have the, we're gonna have a table
that lets you look up the nursing home and care about, right?
And then that table should have like a search
and a filter and a way for you to like dig into it.
And then there's something like the live wildfires map,
which is really about one, giving you an overview
of like how many fires are there right now.
But then two,
two, letting you drill down into areas that you care about
to see kind of the latest data within those areas.
And so that's the map being there for personalization
and discovery, you know.
I think a lot of the interactivity that was just
like about fiddling, you've probably noticed
has like mostly disappeared.
Plus it's a lot, it takes more time to code.
- Yeah, very cool.
You know, we definitely wanna ask you this one question
for sure, because we have so many students here
who are interested in data and storytelling.
And sort of what is like, if you had one piece of advice
for students going out, working on school projects,
or really just wanting to break into
Ellie Times newsroom or other places, what is it?
What should they know?
- One piece of advice, I mean, I don't know.
- Or two or three.
- I can give you a call.
- Yeah, please.
- I mean, to me, this is a thing that has become cliche
and is said by some people who I think are kind of jerks,
but if you race them from your mind, it is true.
You gotta learn to code.
You don't have any, it's just like to really
do this well, you have to learn to code.
And you have to learn to code certain types of things,
not just like coding in general,
but I do think the fundamentals of programming
are so important.
The fundamentals of just like software and package design
are really underrated, just like how do I write a function
and then import it into another file and then reuse it
and like package code.
Like the basics of coding, I think are super important.
And then the sort of applied application of coding
to the types of things we do.
And so that, I think on the one hand,
is kind of data gathering and analysis.
So this is, how do I get data by scraping it
or reading it out of a database or building my own database?
And then how do I analyze it to like interview the data
is how we think about it.
What questions do I have for the data
and how can I write code that will help me get the answers
to those questions?
And so the tool that I teach a lot of classes on
that I like, but it's all debatable
is the Jupyter Notebook with Python data analysis tools.
They're free is kind of the best thing about it.
And the Jupyter environment once you figure out
how to get it running is just a really handy way
to do like step by step kind of data work.
And then on the other side,
there's the sort of how do we tell stories visually
through web development, right?
And that really involves learning fundamentals of HTML and CSS.
You know, again, just the basics are so important.
They're not even in HTML's case.
It's not even that hard, right?
And then how do you use JavaScript to make interactivity
and data visualizations?
I'm a big fan of D3.
And it's also a great way to get better at JavaScript, too,
because the D3 culture is really built around excellence
and programming, which I think is important.
I think there's a lot of free tools that are just about
cutting corners that don't really help you
over the long run become to master that type of thing.
So to me, there's the coding part,
but then there's the journalism part, which is thing two.
And this is where, like when I get applicants for internships
and stuff from data science programs,
which I'm always glad to get and I love to see,
you know, sometimes the people just haven't had the time
or opportunity to really apply their work in a way
that they're making something for the general public
or that has kind of a headline take away like point, you know?
A big part of editing and putting out a piece of journalism
is you kind of have to have like something to say.
And just writing a notebook that asks 10 questions
of the data or just making a graphic
that lets you fiddle with the numbers isn't enough, right?
The things that you're making need to kind of take
that next level of kind of journalistic whatever, you know,
by saying my finding is this.
And here's the headline that says it
and here's the three charts that show it, you know what I mean?
And you kind of like have a takeaway and a point
so that you have something to share.
And so when I see applicants who,
and I don't expect anyone who's being out
to really master any of this,
but when I see people who kind of have clearly put in the effort
to do both of those two things,
to like learn how to do the coding stuff to make stuff,
but also learn how to boil it down
and to make something out of it
for regular people, you know what I mean?
That's when I think you're a strong applicant
and you're sort of beginning the road to become do what we do.
But the reality is is learning how to code takes a while
and the things we're learning,
we're trying to do are emerging and experimental.
And so no one including myself really gets kind of good
at what we're doing until they've spent a couple of years
really apprenticing at it.
And that's just, that's just being human, you know?
- That's great.
That's really humbling.
And I think really honest to share that.
And I hope all the students out there
really get a lot out of that.
That's really helpful.
You know, I don't know if you wanted to kind of
have a wrap up question or...
- Yeah, whatever you guys got,
I'll take, I got a couple of minutes yet.
- Yeah, okay.
Well, well, first of all, thank you for kind of validating
this week for us from what you just said,
the value of coding, open data.
This is all that we've been kind of preaching
in the last couple of days.
Also should mention that if I look up
visual storyteller in the dictionary,
I think I'll find you in there.
You seem to embody that kind of visual storyteller mentality.
But I don't know if there's like one or two final questions.
Maybe somebody can unmute themselves
if you're out there and introduce yourself to Ben
and ask a question, hoping somebody can do that.
- I have a quick question.
- Please.
- And that's about, Ben, I see that you're active
in an organization called Data for Progress.
And I'm wondering if you'd talk about that a little bit.
It sort of ties in with what we've been doing
with humanitarian mapping.
And sort of how you see that kind of mission
converging with what you're doing at the LA Times,
which is obviously more of a commercial than--
- Yeah.
I don't know if I'm familiar with Data for Progress,
but I'm guessing it came up linked
to some other things that I do, you know what I mean?
But like for me personally, open source software
is probably as close as I get to religion.
Nice, but like, and I think is a really underrated
as a solution to a lot of problems.
It just needs more institutional support
from places like UCLA.
But what you guys are providing today, which is great,
you know, but like, and so I've been involved
in a number of kind of open source data gathering
and cleaning efforts related to helping journalists
both improve their skills, but also to kind of
build software and data infrastructure.
So we're not all like replicating each other's work
and we can benefit from kind of group collaboration.
One of those is called the California Civic Data Coalition.
And so this was a foundation funded open source
software project that refines and cleans up
the campaign finance data put up
by the California state government.
So this is the money in our state politics,
like all these Uber ads you're seeing
for Prop 22 right now.
And the data is there, it's just really difficult to access
because it's just in crappy shape.
And so there's kind of like this problem of who's going
to clean it up, right?
And so we created an open source group
to write the software that would be the refinery
for that like raw data, and then all the code
and all the effort is open source as well as the result.
Along the way we invented some bulk data loading
open source software tools, which people now use
for like totally different purposes, you know what I mean?
There's like side benefits to doing that.
And we're replicating that model currently
when it comes to tracking COVID data,
where initially the LA Times was doing 100%
of this COVID tracking ourselves in California,
but we now have a team of people from eight newsrooms
across the state who are helping us kind of gather it
and consolidate this cleaned up database of COVID data.
And I think that there's one, a lot of potential for that,
but two, I think as news organizations get smaller
and struggle, I don't know if there's a better alternative,
like who, you know what I mean?
Other than we just hope the New York Times gets big enough,
they can do it for everybody, you know what I mean?
Like that's really, the commercial solution
is going to be news monopoly, you know,
that's just big enough to do that is what I think.
But, you know, maybe I'm being too pessimistic.
So I think we need to band together
to come up with this alternative.
- Thank you.
Great, how about one last question for Ben?
How about one of the questions?
- I have a question.
- There we go, please.
- So I love your neighborhood map,
which is, I know, which has been on the page
for a while now, it's so great.
And I use it in my classes to talk to instruct students,
well, instruct students about two things,
one about the concept of place
and another about the concept
of volunteer geographic information.
And I'm curious if you guys have done other projects
that you think are within the realm
of like volunteer geographic information.
So like people actually map like-
- Yep, that project is one of my great white whales
and that we haven't really revived it.
There was a, the plan was to do it last year
for this census, but other things have come up.
And just so people know,
there is no official source of neighborhoods in LA County,
even though we all feel that we live in one.
And so about 10 years ago with some of my colleagues,
we sort of tried to pull the public
and then divide up LA County into, you know,
the LA Times neighborhoods at least.
And then we connected those kind of like
with the legos of census tracts.
So then all the areas have all this metadata
about demographics that are then merged with them,
which has allowed us to do dozens of investigative
and analytical stories to compare East LA to West LA,
you know what I mean?
It's not more in social science.
And one of my personal ambitions is for our team
to be more of a social science data provider.
We're trying to do that a little bit here with COVID,
but I would love to sort of be able to publish
sort of like the machine readable atlas
of LA demographics by neighborhood or something
so that we could see more and more people
able to do that type of analytical work.
But at the core of it was this crowdsourcing effort
'cause we didn't want to do it entirely alone.
So we sort of put out our own version of the maps
and then we had people tell us how wrong we were
and we modified them and you can't please everybody.
There's definitely flaws,
but that was kind of a collaborative process.
You know, that's the type of thing
that we haven't turned into like it.
We're going to do something like that every month,
but there's a few examples through the years
that I've had a lot of fun working on.
Like we finally, we're going to do the like a few years ago,
the like, what is the East Side story in the LA Times?
You know what I mean?
Where everybody brings out their grievances, you know,
and I will tell you as long as I am the data
and graphics editor, the East Side begins at the LA River.
I'm sorry, everybody who lives on Sunset,
you don't live on the East Side, sorry, you know what I mean?
But like, but we know people disagree, you know what I mean?
Like there is no answer.
And so we did like a one-off that was sort of
in that same tradition where it was,
here's a map of LA, draw the East Side, right?
And we had hundreds of people like draw them all.
And then we made this composite map
that was like everybody's East Side like overlaid.
And it was a little abstract and already, you know what I mean?
I don't know if it was like the clearest data visualization
ever drawn, but it sort of had this fun effort of like,
here's the splatter of like what everybody thinks, you know?
And though I'm sure our readership is biased
in a certain direction.
But so like that was an example of that, I guess.
- Yeah.
- You know, to me, the crowdsourcing thing that's out there
that nobody does much with Viz,
which we could do with Quakebot,
is the like, did you feel an earthquake data from like USGS?
I think it's like all of there for every earthquake
and like nobody really does much with it, you know?
I know the scientists at USGS do,
but like, I don't know if the news media does.
Yeah.
- Right.
Cool.
Thank you.
- All right.
Yeah, no, there's a whole bunch of chatter
about that project you're talking about mapping Los Angeles.
- Yeah.
- It's many of us fondly remember that kind of,
hey, we can contribute to defining boundaries,
which is not something we're used to.
Boundaries are usually defined by somebody up there.
And we abide by those boundaries.
And here's the LA Times saying,
hey, you define your own boundaries.
So that was a really neat project.
And still to this day in the urban planning department,
that's a go to resource for doing neighborhood level analysis.
- Yeah.
I was absolutely just going to say that.
I mean, I think the impact of that project in the classroom,
I just don't know if that kind of reaches you all,
but like, I mean, that is in so many different classes,
so many different students use that as sort of like,
understanding LA at this point.
- Yes, we have census tracts.
Yes, we have these other boundaries,
but those particular boundaries in that work
is just super, super influential in the classroom.
- Yeah.
I mean, to me, I just see all the times we fail to revive it.
So I feel a little guilty with that.
But like, you know, we kind of have, I have some ideas.
I might be like, this is one of these things
where like internally it gets caught up in the politics of like,
do we need a hyper local neighborhood news product?
You know what I mean?
And like, it's hard to have a conversation internally
without it being caught up with like traditional coverage.
It's my belief that it should be more of a data application
and like kind of like a social science hub
that is like easy enough for the average person
to understand, you know what I mean?
That's just like what is, you know,
Chevy bills or whatever, you know?
And I would like to kind of narrow kind of the mission
of it to really focus on that kind of popularizing
the demographics thing.
And so my hope is, is that we can do that
when the new census data comes out.
But as you know, it's the ACS is where the action really is.
So it doesn't matter.
I kind of wonder if we could partner that with like,
can I give you my pet idea?
And you guys can tell me if it's terrible.
With like a gentrification analysis.
- Oh, yeah.
- If you like that, yeah.
'Cause I did some reading
and you guys may know this better than me,
but there's these like academic definitions
of gentrification, which as far as I can tell,
are kind of limited to a sort of post-war redevelopment
sort of framework of like, how old is the housing stock?
And how recently has it been replenished?
And what is the change in housing value been, right?
And so like, you could, I look at those methods
and I could take these longitudinal census databases.
I can do that for every census tract
and then I could tell you what's the most gentrified neighborhood
in LA like that way, right?
That would be one way.
But like my hunch is that that's not enough.
Like in our 21st century life,
there's sort of this Brooklynized idea of gentrification,
which has to do with cultural products, right?
And commerce and like that kind of thing, you know what I mean?
Like what is the business in Highland Park now
on that strip on Fig versus 10 years ago, right?
Used to be a Latino typewriter shop
and now it's a hipster cocktail bar or whatever, you know?
And I think that's what people have in mind
when they send you an interpretation today.
And so like what I'm kind of reaching for
is could you come up with a metric
that would try to capture that
and then integrate it with the older metrics
into like a kind of more up-to-date gentrification index
or something, do anybody have any ideas
or have read anything that smiles ahead of me on this?
- Well, you know, there's a Center for Neighborhood Knowledge
here at UCLA that does a lot of research.
I don't know if you know Paul Wong,
he's a professor who--
- I don't know. - Wong worked with models
of gentrification and they have a site,
a project called Urban Displacement,
collaboration with Berkeley and UCLA
where they have index S for gentrification.
- No, really?
- It just talks about the need for us, you know,
in academia and also to let you know,
like UCLA is launching this kind of data acts initiative.
So it sounds like we are,
once that behind you guys, but we're right there
in terms of our efforts to think about,
like you said, you know, the importance of coding
in kind of the more social sciences,
which isn't traditionally been the case.
So just to think about how us in academia,
I mean, I feel such a stronger bond with you
through what we've been discussing today
and the importance that we work together
to create some meaningful stories
that can inform policy decisions across our communities.
- Yeah, I also love, I really love the idea
of kind of looking at sort of alternative data sources.
I was on a call yesterday and a workshop yesterday
actually looking at the Getty's new Riche project.
And they're putting all these images out there.
And this workshop was really trying to understand
how to look at those images, you know,
in this, you know, cultural production,
the streets that were photographed,
historically looking at, you know, racial change over time
and really talking about gentrification
and how a data set like that with those images
could be used with, you know, all these sources
that you're talking about, but other data sets
that are cultural and kind of trying to, you know,
look at that and also how to sort of code those images
and doing that coding so that it actually is, you know,
doing the work that we want it to do
in terms of understanding, you know, the displacement
or whatever's happening.
And not just sort of saying like, oh, you know,
this was here before and now it's gone,
but like, well, why is it gone?
And really kind of, you know, putting the point onto that.
So yeah, it's really interesting.
And I think you're right.
I mean, I think what we've been talking about
with, you know, really learning how to, you know,
build coding and, you know, also just stepping back
and being able to kind of piece, I think,
like really different data sets.
And the thing that we were talking about yesterday too
is just sort of understanding that world of data
and kind of, especially I think for things
like gentrification, kind of stepping out
and kind of looking at or trying to understand it
in a way that's local and trying to find sources
that maybe aren't that typical, you know, census,
you know, way of understanding it.
So I don't know, I love it.
Yeah.
- There's a guy at Harvard I found he did a paper read
used Yelp data and then he tried to like correlate
the arrival of certain types of businesses
with other gentrification indicators, you know,
like educated population or whatever.
And so there might be something there, you know,
but I kind of imagine the index.
You take like the traditional metric of like buildings
or whatever, you know, you add in the racial dynamic
of, you know, white invasion, as I've learned,
it's called in some papers.
And then you maybe add like a third cultural dimension
of these products and then you like mix those into like
a radar chart or like an index or something
and that'd be kind of cool.
My bet is what Adams would be number one.
That's my bet guys.
- I would say from personal experience
with Brooklyn and here in LA, the first major indicator
should be when the real estate agent decides
to change the name of the name.
- There you go.
That's another one.
- That's an indicator.
- One thing I learned looking at the literature too,
I thought was interesting is traditionally only like
the lowest quartile could ever be thought of
as having gentrified.
So you had to be depressed to ever undergo the process.
And I don't think that people think about it that way
today anymore.
Like, 'cause when I ran the traditional numbers,
I saw that Venice Beach had a really high score
on some of the values but wouldn't have been considered
because it was already a pretty wealthy place to begin with.
Right?
And so like there's this way in which I think
the traditional numeric framework doesn't mesh
with how people really think about it
or talk about it today.
And like, that's the thing I just feel like
there must be some way to wrestle that.
But.
- That could be a,
and this is a very geographically nerdy
but a modifiable aerial unit problem issue
where because you're looking at Venice as a whole.
- Right, we've predefined it.
- Yeah.
- Very wealthy parts get, you know,
averaged with the less wealthy parts.
So those.
- That's a good point.
- Yeah.
- Mm.
- But I'm thinking also that with the sort of combining
what Andy was talking about with the coding
and like maybe taking for each neighborhood,
choosing kind of like the commercial strip
and looking at Google Street View
and sort of like coding that over time
for the main, like the main drags of different neighborhoods.
- Yeah.
Or even if we did the number for the whole county,
you could pick the place that had the highest
and up new merit score and then go in
and do that closer study on that place.
- Yeah.
- You know, and then you wouldn't have to do everywhere.
- Right.
- I also have to think about how to do less.
Sorry.
(laughing)
- Now, I mean, I think that's one of the things
that we all struggle to is sort of kind of, you know,
looking at LA, but I think a lot of us push our students
and just people that we work with to focus in on areas.
And I think that's sort of like a nice bridge to,
you know, I think what you at the times do
is kind of putting in the person into our data stories.
And like, you know, not always sort of like having that
bird's eye view of everybody, but like, let's zoom in.
Let's like really kind of understand what this data set
is doing on this street, on this block.
- Yep.
We talk about them and like, there's usually,
there's like two different couples we're looking for.
There's like, there's either Mr. and Mrs. Outlier
or there's Mr. and Mrs. Central Tendency.
And like kind of depending on like which story
you're telling, you're sort of like aiming
for those people, you know.
- That's great.
I love that.
- I feel like we're in a newsroom right now
making decisions for the next story.
But I wanna wrap us up here,
taking too much of your time.
Thank you so much.
The conversations in the chat room has been just nonstop.
You've touched a lot of topics that really mean
so much to many of us.
So just wanna say a big thank you to Ben.
I'm sure it's shared by all of us here.
There you go.
And Ben, let's definitely get together again.
When there's a little bit more time to relax.
I don't know when that would be.
But I'd love to kind of have a conversation
about how we in academia can work closer together
with you guys at the LA Times.
- Great.
- Yeah.
- For having me.
- Thank you.
Thank you for being so generous with your time.
It's really amazing.
- Mm-hmm.
Thank you so much.
- Sorry, I was late.
- I love the new luck.
I love the-
(laughing)
- I'm gonna report that to my wife.
- All right, thank you so much, Ben.
- Thank you, Ben.
- Mm-hmm.
- Bye.